- Hey folks and welcome
to the Learn UI Design
Lesson on Simplicity.
Today we're gonna be covering
six strategies for making
your designs look clean,
simple, neat, modern, et cetera.
Those adjectives by the way,
are the most common
adjectives that clients use
to describe what they want
you to design for them.
So being able to make something
just look neat and clean
and simple and modern,
whatever, that's an
extremely valuable skill
and once you've mastered
that, achieving other brands,
whether you're going for something
that looks very luxurious
or very friendly, very techie,
futuristic, whatever it is,
you're building on top of
the lessons in this video.
Not around them, you're
building on top of them.
So it's almost difficult to overstate
how important this six-pronged approach
for making simple designs is.
You are going to be hearing it
throughout the remainder of this course
and I want you to be saying
these strategies to yourself
as you approach any design
that comes across your desk
and this approach will
give you the power to take,
again, any design, whether
it's maybe just a sketch or a
wireframe from a UX designer
who you might be working with
or even if it's say a client comes to you
with kind of a half-finished
design or maybe
an MVP prototype that they've already
put on the web and it doesn't really
look good but they want
you to spiff it up.
It doesn't matter, in
any of those scenarios,
you can take this
framework and the six ideas
in it and start applying them
and make a ton of progress
into making the design look
neat and clean and simple.
All right, so let's
start talking about it.
So I'm gonna start by
just doing a very brief
review of the six
strategies of simplicity.
I'm not gonna go into super detail here
but at least you'll
know what we're covering
over the rest of the
lesson and as these kinda
cycle through my mind and
what I'm talking about,
you can just keep thinking
of this same list here.
So the first three strategies
we've already covered,
alignment, spacing, and consistency.
I'm gonna assume that you know
enough about those already.
The fourth, fifth and six,
these are the new ones.
The fourth strategy is
one that I call lightening
and by lightening, I just
mean removing emphasis
from something, making
it a little bit lighter.
It doesn't have to be lighter
in the sense that it's
closer to white, just lighter
in the sense that it doesn't
draw your attention as much.
The first three strategies are ones that
you apply to elements
that are important enough
that you definitely want
them visible on your screen.
The second three are kind of
the less important elements.
You're not gonna take an
important element and lighten it
but if there's something that's essential
but not super important, that's
where you use lightening.
Hiding is another one like lightening.
Hiding just means you're taking
an element and hiding it by default.
You're making it not visible by default.
It's still in the app, it
still might be essential
but maybe you put it in a
menu or in a hover state
or on a different screen or
a pop-up or whatever it is.
The point is there's some elements that
you just don't want to
be visible by default
and the more you can do that,
the simpler of an appearance
your screen will have.
And the final strategy is removing.
This is simple, it just means
getting rid of that thing
entirely from the app.
So the whole idea behind the
simplicity framework here
is you just go through every element
on the page and you say
can I align this better?
Can I space this better?
Can I make it consistent with anything?
Or if it's not super
important, can I lighten it?
If it's even less important,
maybe you can hide it
and if it's just totally unimportant,
you can remove it entirely.
But the point is if you keep these six
strategies in mind, it's gonna give you
a very powerful framework for
making messy UI look cleaner.
So as always, I want to
apply it to an example
and this particular example
is an app for veterinarians
and this page of the app
has to do with the idea
that if a dog eats some
chocolate, first of all,
that's poisonous for the
dog but second of all,
you might need to know some information
about how to treat that dog
and so this is a little calculator
for vets that you can enter
in the weight of the dog,
the weight of the chocolate,
the type of the chocolate
and you get some information
out about what to do next.
Now this example is extremely similar
to a lot of the examples that I see
all the time from my students and readers.
So even if you think this
is like fairly messy UI
and you have a sense of
how you would fix it,
just know that it's still
a very valuable skill
to be able to explicitly go through this
and understand what you're
doing as you clean it up.
But it's not unrealistic at all
that clients or employers will come to you
with apps that look very much like this.
Now as far as this six-pronged
approach to simplicity goes,
when you're kind of advanced at it,
I think you'll be able to like open up
a page and you'll just have a gut instinct
of what you want to start changing first
that'll kind of give you
the most bang for your buck.
Like for instance, I look at these inputs
and I think immediately about making them
more consistent and
full width and that will
make them feel very aligned
and crisp and so on.
I think that'd be a good thing
to do but we'll get there.
What I kind of want to do is
start by talking a little bit
about the new strategies and
how they might pop up here
and specifically, we can talk
about them in the context
of this top menu and this
bottom menu-like element.
So if you remember, the fourth strategy
is lightening and that's
something that you apply
to an element that you
want to keep on the page
but just currently seems a
little bit too important.
And like one way of saying what
is too important is to do a squint test,
the same thing that we've
talked about already
and even just doing a
squint test on the top half
of this screen, I can see
there's a nice title here.
This looks like some
important kind of title too
and then there's a really
big light blob right here,
which I wouldn't immediately
be sure what that is.
Of course in this case, it's
this question mark icon.
Probably it's gonna give
me some sort of help
but what's weird about
this is this question
mark is essentially in size 30 font
which compared to this title at size 17,
this thing is just huge
and oversized and it's just
too big and attention-grabbing
for its own importance.
So one thing we could do
is start by removing that
and then we're gonna go
ahead and say add in an icon
from something like the
Material Design Icon Library.
So the Help icon is the one
that I want, gonna grab it here.
Then I'm gonna center it nicely
in sort of this top
slot area in the header
and I'm gonna go make it white
because it's on a colored background,
that's the best way to do
it and then I'm actually
going to apply another form of lightening.
So far, I've lightened it
in the sense that I've made it smaller.
I'm just like reduced kind of
its pop or it's visual emphasis.
But sizes isn't the only way to do it.
I can literally do it by making it
less contrasting against its background
using like an opacity 50%,
70%, something like that.
The fifth strategy is hiding
and that's something that I do to
anything that feels like it belongs
in the app but just doesn't belong here.
So one great example
is these three actions
along the bottom, reset
inputs, print and scan,
these actually look in most iPhone apps
like the major app navigational
destinations of the app
and yet these are not kind
of the main destinations
of the app or the main
sections of the app.
These are just three actions
that you can take on this page.
So instead what I'm gonna do is take them
and presumably they're
not all that important.
I don't think I'm very often gonna
want to print or scan this information.
So I would say these actions
actually better belong in a menu.
Now one very common way to do menus on iOS
is to say have some little icon up here
which I can pull down a menu from.
It's actually Google
that uses this pattern
of three dots to represent a menu.
But the point is I could actually
replace this question
mark icon with a menu icon
and then whatever help I
would get by clicking here,
that help could just be
one more item in the menu
along with Print and
whatever else was there.
So again, I might do a
slightly lesser opacity
'cause it doesn't need
to be super important.
I could try 100%, whatever,
there's some leeway in
exactly what you do there.
Again, I'm gonna get it
centered nicely there
and now the app is once again simpler
in that it no longer has this bottom bar
of infrequently used
actions visible by default.
The sixth strategy is just
to remove whatever is
completely unnecessary
and one example from this header here
is this little picture of chocolate.
It adds nothing to the title,
so I can remove it and
certainly nothing bad happens.
I might also consider
making the title a little
bit more useful given
the purpose of the page,
"Chocolate Ingested" or
something like that that kind of
describes the case that brings
you to use this calculator.
So we're gonna talk a lot
more about lightening, hiding
and removing but that's
the general gist of things.
One tool that goes arm-in-arm with
the six strategies of
simplicity is the squint test.
We've already talked about it a little bit
but it's just something you're gonna want
to be doing very frequently as you try
and make an app simpler and neater looking
and so one example of how we'd use it here
is if I kind of take a
high level description
of this app or this page,
I would say you enter
in some inputs here and then
you get some results here
and if that could be communicated
even to someone who's squinting or even
if there's a blurry overlay on top,
that there's kind of like some
inputs and then maybe some
other information below, that
would be really, really good.
I think one way to do that is
to style them consistently.
In other words, instead of having
just one card that surrounds everything,
we'd actually kind of do a style
where there's maybe two cards
and one card has the inputs on it
and the other card has the
information that is output.
Now I don't believe this image
of chocolate is really adding anything.
So I'm gonna use the removal strategy
and just go ahead and get rid of that.
But already I now have sort
of a neater UI to work with
in that these two cards make it clear
that there's kind of two
main sections of the screen.
And let's talk about card
styling just for a second.
If you remember from the spacing lesson,
one thing I said is that you
can use white space in place of
any other border that you have
or any other real separator.
So one thing we're gonna try is just
removing some of these separators,
in particular the stroke
around these cards.
I can definitely get rid of that
and then one other thing is it's generally
a design faux pas to have a rounded
corner that meets the edge of the screen.
That's cool if this content
slides in from the bottom
but there's really no reason
for these to be rounded.
So I'm actually gonna
bring the border radius
down to zero and then I'm
also gonna remove the shadow.
That's one other sort of type
of separator and you can just see it.
I'm just gonna remove
it because by default,
I want to get rid of all this stuff
and just make things as
clean and simple as possible.
Really the name of the game here
is remove it now and then
add in later as necessary.
But default to removing stuff now.
Go as simple as possible
and then add in whatever is necessary.
So this is generally working all right
but I really want to make this display
and this display feel very consistent
so that even to someone
doing a squint test,
you can see clearly that
there's two parts to the screen.
So I'm actually gonna give
this a little bit more space
and then we're gonna worry
about this title right here.
First of all, again, think
about the spacing lesson.
I say background color
changes are a very common way
of denoting what element
is separated from the rest.
Well, that's one way to
do it but you know what?
There's others as well.
We could simply put this
kind of above the card
and then we're also going to left-align it
and the big reason to
left-align this title
is because in general, aligning text left
is always gonna give you a greater sense
of alignment or a greater
feel of alignment.
It's gonna buy you a bit more alignment
with the same elements on the page.
So it's just the way we want to default.
Now I'm actually gonna title this "Inputs"
and this might be something
like "Results" or whatever.
And now that all this
is looking fairly good,
I'm going to dive into working on
these little inputs right here.
Now if you remember from
the consistency lesson,
I said one very important element
of consistency is being consistent
with the other apps that
are already out there
and one way this comes into play here
is when I click in the pounds
and I edit this number,
this is actually just a translation
in kilograms of the same value
and so if I edit this one,
this one updates and vice
versa and it's the same
with the ounces ingested
versus grams ingested.
Now to me, this feels
a little bit confusing
because it's not often that you see two
text boxes on one row and
that means enter in one
and the other's gonna
just automatically update.
So I want to be more consistent.
Maybe I'll just have a single text box
that says "Amount Ingested"
and then it could be
like a small dropdown or
something where you choose
between pounds and
kilograms and likewise for,
sorry, the weight of the
dog and then the amount
ingested and then I can
choose my units on the side.
So that's one thing
that'll make these two rows
feel consistent with how
other apps would do this.
But then another way I can add in
consistency is remember consistency first.
If I'm adding in another form control,
in this case here's this
totally separate drop-down,
this is given its own style.
It doesn't have a border,
it doesn't have a shadow.
In no way does it look like
this other form control right here.
Well as much as possible, I
want to go consistency first
and have things kind of
default to looking the same
and then if I make any differences
or inconsistencies to them, I'm only gonna
do that where I have
rationale for doing so.
So let's actually just
slide this off so that
I can kind of work things
through consistency first.
Of course in sizing, we
know that the default
iOS form control needs to be
44 pixels tall, there we go.
So that looks good
there and then I'm gonna
just kind of grab the same
thing and bring it down here.
And ultimately this will be a text input
of the dog's weight and this'll
be like a little selector
and if I tap here, I'll have
maybe some sort of modal that
quickly allows me to pick
between pounds and kilograms.
Now we used the Material
design Icon Set there,
so I'm gonna do option + command + P
which brings up the last
extension I used in Figma
and I want the little down caret.
This is just a very easy
way to create a dropdown.
And of course, I'm gonna align that well
by centering it vertically
in its bounding box.
I'll give it a little
extra margin right there.
I think this needs an S.
So now this is interesting
because it's very consistent.
The text box and the dropdown
actually look really, really similar.
I could imagine that
somewhere else in the app,
this actually becomes a bit of an issue
but as long as it's not, I'm
gonna default to consistency
and so let's do the
same thing where we make
a similar control for the chocolate type.
A little space in here,
maybe default to something like 12 pixels.
And then I suppose actually one smart way
to do this is to highlight
these three things,
press option + command + G.
It's gonna make them into their own frame
and then I can say for
instance, we're going to, oops,
we're gonna hold this on the right side,
the pounds will be anchored on the left
and this background needs to stretch
left to right and top to bottom.
So that way when I duplicate this,
pull this over, it behaves appropriately
and I can say the chocolate type
is dark chocolate or what have you
and then finally in the name
of consistency first, for
the third row, that has the
same format as the first row.
So we'll just duplicate
it and go from there.
Now I can unlock this background layer,
maybe do something like 12
pixels of padding there.
Looks good enough.
Give it a little space above
the title and likewise,
we'll give the title a little space too
and that is looking much better.
The only little issue I see
here is related to spacing.
It's the idea of internal spacing
being less than external spacing.
Because the space between
this and this is actually
very little compared to the
space between the control
and the label is attached
to, it almost feels
like this is kind of one unit,
at the squint test level,
this is one unit of this area
and these three labels are another unit
and that's not really the case.
If anything, I want the user to first
perceive this as a set of rows.
So I'm actually gonna go ahead
and add divider lines in.
This is a great reason why one would break
using white space as the
only divider or something
is just you need to
more clearly convey that
even if the spacing
isn't quite working out,
this is one unit and this
is a totally separate thing.
Nice, so I'm gonna get
rid of all this stuff
and then we move on to the results here.
Basically my main goal is to try
and do something that is as consistent
as possible with this display here.
So maybe I'll do something
where I'm kind of using rows.
For instance, I might take this "Emergency
Treatment Advised" and
perhaps if you click that,
it launches into exactly what
emergency treatment you need.
It's not necessarily a huge
deal exactly how that works.
If you remember from the alignment lesson,
since this is rounded,
I could even bump it
a pixel or two to the left,
that's not a huge deal.
To be otherwise consistent
with the spacing,
there's six pixels above
and below everything
here as far as I know,
oops, that was nine.
Now I might do something like make this
font size the same as this font size
because it's kind of that
same standard body text.
Again, just being consistent
as much as possible.
We want everything nice and lined up.
We'll actually move this down
to deal with it in just a second.
Center text, I don't have anything
really against it but again, it's just not
as easy to get that feeling of alignment.
So I'm gonna change it up a little bit.
I'm not gonna use a bold label here
'cause this one is already bold.
But what I might do is just give this
like a 70% opacity and
then it kind of feels
like a label for the data
below, that works nicely.
And then you can
duplicate this and finally
add in something, again a
label, even though there
wasn't a label initially
for this equation, I'm gonna
add one just so it makes
these two rows consistent.
So I might say something like
"Total Methylxanthines
Ingested."
Consistency first, since
I'm making more kind
of body text, I'm gonna start by grabbing
the text I already have and
we can type in the data.
85 milligrams of theobromine.
13.2 milligrams caffeine
and 99.12 milligrams
total
methylxanthines.
Since this is the important bit,
I will just bold it like that.
But there we go, that
feels like a much more
consistent way to display all this.
And now that we have both sections done,
I can maybe get this a
little bit closer here.
My goal is just to kind
of like squint at it
as I do this and say
what feels like sort of
the right amount where my
eye very easily understands
that I'm looking at two
separate things here?
And then you might notice I'm just
adding some borders at
the top and bottom here.
This is actually consistent
with how iOS styles its own
lists but it is nice because
it kind of just adds a little
more separation between the
list and the label for it.
So there we go.
I'm not saying that's the
only way of doing things.
This is just one take at it.
But you can see by taking those six ideas
of alignment, spacing,
consistency, lightening,
hiding and removing, we've made something
that's quite messy into something that's
actually quite a bit
neater and easier to parse.
Now we're gonna set our sights
on a little more complicated example.
This one is a submission
or based very closely
on a submission from Learn
UI Design student Brayden.
So thank you for that, Brayden.
It's a kind of typical clean
and simple job tracker.
There's some orders that
have come in and people
need to go install roller
blinds or something like that.
Honestly it doesn't really matter
exactly what the details are.
The point is we're gonna be
taking our six strategies
of simplicity and going
through basically top to bottom
and doing everything up and
making this look much better.
Now just like the mobile example,
I want to start by
talking a little bit more
about those new three ideas that we have,
lightening, hiding and removing.
So with lightening, I think it's worth
mentioning one thing
that is just absolutely
a prime candidate for getting lightened
is what I call meta
content or meta elements.
So like for instance,
this reference number,
this is useful data that is
being presented to the user.
But something like these
borders right here,
it's not really data.
It's more like it shows
how the data is structured,
kind of what the relationship is.
In this case, these borders
show that this is one cell
and this is another cell
and that's another cell
and this is a row and what have you.
So a lot of times content like this
like borders or shadows,
background color changes,
even characters used for
kind of dividing things up,
maybe even bullet points
fit into this category,
all of these things I call meta content
and meta content or
meta elements are often
the first things that you go to lighten.
So for instance, I mean let
me just duplicate this here
so we can compare it
before and after but then
let's go and just take out
some of these meta elements.
The borders, going, background
color changes, going.
We are gonna fix up this table
towards the end of the demo here.
But the first thing we're
gonna do is remove all of this.
And of course, this isn't to say that
every table doesn't
have any borders at all.
It's just saying we're
removing these borders for now
and we're gonna add in
something that is exactly
as heavy as we feel like
we need and no heavier.
I'm also gonna lighten this header.
I think maybe the easiest way to do it
might be to turn it into a background.
I pressed shift + X to swap
the stroke with the fill.
So now it is just the stroke.
I'm gonna move it all the way to the back
here and I'm gonna move it to the outside,
which should turn it into
just this bottom stroke.
Give it a very light
opacity and there we go.
Now the only thing distinguishing
the header is this very light gray line.
So that's a good way to lighten things up.
I'm gonna lock it in place
just for a sec here and
that's gonna allow me to select
all these other elements.
Now actually, I kind
of want a default color
and this text color seems
like it'll fit the bill.
If I remember correctly,
everything in this app
more or less uses variations
on the same color,
an idea that we will talk
about in the color unit.
So I can highlight all of this stuff
and then I'm going to go give it
a more visible treatment here.
We'll just use this default
color for everything
and this actually said zero.
There were no new alerts, so
I can remove that entirely.
But yeah, now the header background
metadata or meta element
is appropriately lightened.
The sidebar is now
distinguished only by spacing,
which seems to work fine.
We can talk more about
it in a sec and our table
we sort of stripped
out all of the borders,
which of course we will add
in to some degree but again,
we're just starting by
removing as much as possible
and we'll go and add
it back as we need it.
Another prime target for lightening
is anything that gets repeated
and we'll come back to
this when we do the table.
But for instance, if I
have these three bells
and if this is just something that
appears on every single row of the table,
I can actually have it be quite a bit
less visible and still
attract people's attention.
Now in this case, these three
rows have specific alerts.
So I don't really want to
remove this but it's just an
idea we'll talk about more in
the Lists and Tables lesson.
Something may look good if
you just design a single row
but then when you
duplicate that row a bunch,
that element now attracts
your attention way too much.
So a lot of times,
you just have to lighten
repeating elements.
Now when lightening, it is
really good to use the squint
test and when I kind of
squint my eyes right here,
imagining that this is
a table, I'm actually
a little stuck on what
the title of the page is.
To me, this almost looks a
little bit more like a title.
This definitely looks like
a sidebar, that's good.
This looks like some
help and profile stuff,
that's good and I can tell these controls
probably have something
to do with the table.
So overall it's not like
we're in an awful situation
but I am gonna want to beef up
the title just a little bit.
Of course, I could also
consider moving this thing that
looks like a title over to
where these other controls are.
One thing that's important to be aware of
is most controls have sort
of a natural maximum width
that you shouldn't go above and beyond.
So for this search bar,
I really don't need it
stretching all the way across the screen.
I'm gonna have it be quite a bit smaller
and if I'm gonna keep these buttons here,
I'm gonna default to having
them be a consistent height.
The color we can come
back to but they just
look a little bit neater
and cleaner right here.
And then we can work on
the title a little bit.
So "Job Tracking" is indeed
the title of the page
but then there's also a view,
which is in some sense the important part.
In this case, "Active Orders" is the view
and there's a number of ones
that I can switch between.
So one thing I might do
is just get rid of some
of this stuff except for "Job
Tracking" and "Active Orders"
and make these look a
little bit more important.
I'll bold both of them and
"Job Tracking" I'll make
a bit bigger but actually I'm
gonna see if "Active Orders"
looks the best as kind
of the title of the page.
To do this, I can lighten the
"Job Tracking" title right
there and then I can bring in
this control from the side.
Of course, vertically centering it.
I'm thinking about center
of pixel mass here.
Tighten that up and that
looks much more like a title.
If I want to align other things to it,
I will just put in a little ruler.
There we go.
Now I feel like my squint
test already gives me
a much clearer idea of the
overall layout of the page.
So so far, so good.
All right, so we talked about lightening
some elements like the repeating elements
or kind of the meta content on the page.
There's other things that also
we're just gonna want to hide.
So in this case, I go straight
into looking at these buttons here.
Hide details is actually something
that just hides some of
the columns in this table.
But if we do our job, we should
be able to display them all by default
and have it be a manageable
number of columns.
So let's just assume we can remove that.
This Refresh Data button refreshes
whatever is displayed here on the table.
But honestly, we could probably
hide that too in a certain sense.
Rather than make the
user actively refresh,
either we should just do it whenever
there's a data update, do it automatically
or if that's too expensive,
perhaps just prompt
the user with some sort
of message that might
appear at the bottom
of the screen that says
"Refresh the Page" or "Click Here" to get
the new data that's part of this table.
Likewise, there are some tutorials here
next to this little information icon
but these tutorials in my mind,
unless we're really trying to
direct a lot of users to them,
they can probably go
in this little dropdown
right here and this is a drop down that
is related to whoever the current user is.
So I'd imagine I'm gonna find things
like Log Out or Settings and that also
feels like a really good
place for tutorials.
Again, if I want to direct a
lot of users to the tutorials,
if that's some feature
we're trying to push,
I might make it even more visible.
Instead of being here,
there might be some color
to it or it might kind
of slide in from the side
of the screen or just be somewhere else
where it does get an
attention-attracting treatment.
But for now, I can assume
we're gonna use the hiding strategy.
Now we're also going to be talking
about hiding a lot of stuff in this table.
But we will kind of
deal with the table last
since it's the most
complex part of the page.
As far as the rest of the page goes,
I think that's most of the
stuff I'd want to hide.
All right, so that's
the lightening strategy
and the hiding strategy.
The sixth one is removal.
What can we just like
downright get rid of?
I think one element that
we can probably get rid of
pretty safely is this Minimize
Sidebar button right here.
The sidebar doesn't actually attract
too much attention and
if we do our jobs right,
it should look pretty nice anyways.
Now just doing that makes it clear
that I actually really want to have this
Job Tracker logo aligned
here and let's maybe
move this so there's just
20 pixels to the side.
Yeah, there we go, that looks nice.
The removal strategy works really well
for anything that everyone
agrees we just don't need
but it also can work well if you can,
say, convince your client that we don't
need something in this
version of the software.
Say "Hey boss, let's actually wait
for users to complain
about this being missing
before we decide if we want
to put it back in or not."
It's the easiest decision in the world
to add something in that your users want.
It's much harder to remove something
when you're not necessarily sure.
So we're gonna make the hard choice now,
we're just gonna remove it
and then we can always
put it back in later.
And by the way, another
example of when you
can remove stuff is say for
mobile versions of a screen.
It doesn't really apply to this
because we're just looking
at it on desktop but
it could be very reasonable
that say in an app like this,
there's certain things that
I don't see on the mobile
version of this app but if
there was a desktop site,
I would see those things.
So just bear that in mind,
removing something doesn't
just mean removing it period.
It might mean removing
it from this version.
it on mobile, et cetera.
It might mean removing
Okay, now the story so far
is we started with this very messy screen
and we have lightened,
removed and hidden a bunch
of things that we didn't
think were very necessary.
In a big way, those latter
three strategies of the six
strategies of simplicity are
what gets you to the stripped
down, bare bones elements
of what you actually need.
Now we're gonna use more of
the first three strategies,
alignment, consistency and
spacing to kind of determine
how we lay out the stuff
that we do know we need.
So let's start at the top, Job Tracker.
What I'm gonna do is just
kind of center that logo here,
20 pixels of space there on
that side, that looks good.
Now I'm actually gonna start doing
this header by removing this stuff here
and the big reason why
is consistency first.
I'm gonna start with a font
size that I know I like.
So let's go see, this is 16,
that sounds like a perfect
default and I'm going to,
I'm actually gonna use the same
drop down icon from Material Design.
Consistency first once again.
Bring it over here, put it in close, oops.
I'm gonna center these vertically and then
make sure they have fairly
even spacing around them.
So that is 20 pixels on all
three sides, that looks good.
Now I'm gonna take this 'cause
this is a Material Design icon as well.
Because there's no new alerts,
I can make it really quite light,
like maybe 50%, perhaps even 30%
and then I'll do something
like 20 pixels of spacing.
Now it's gonna be the same on
all sides, that works well.
I could take this Search icon too
and maybe I will just grab
this search bar right here.
But one thing I'm definitely gonna do
is give it our theme
color, make it much lighter
with like say one, pressing
one to get 10% opacity
and then I'm gonna kind
of expand it a little bit
and actually this might just
feel like a lot of lines here.
I will play around with swapping
the fill and the border there.
Now I clicked and dragged some
text over from the other side
here and that's just so the
baselines line up right here.
I can now put in this text
something like "Search App."
Make it, I don't know, 50 or 60% opacity
so that it's a good kind of hint text
and we're gonna make sure
the margins are consistent.
Then I'm going to group this
and just move it a couple pixels closer
so now there's consistent
spacing right here
and then finally I have this new dropdown
but I'm actually gonna just like style
that a little bit more like a button
and maybe I can turn it into a button
by pressing shift + A there and
this will say "New."
I need to make this white,
can't see it at all.
And we'll make it bold
and then I want to make
this white as well.
Oh wait, actually what I'm gonna
be doing is adding a Plus icon here.
So if this is 32 pixels tall,
I want to be consistency first,
this button needs to be the same height.
So let me actually press
option + command + P,
go grab a Plus, or what is it, New?
Add, here we go.
I'm gonna make it white and then
I'm gonna drop it into this button.
Now this already seems to be
the right height, which is good
but I do want the contents
instead to be centered
and let's go ahead and just add in
maybe little bit more padding
on some of these sides.
There we go.
And we'll use that same 20 pixels
of space that everything else has.
One thing that strikes
me is I could actually
take the text color and maybe
go find a more vivid blue.
It's still that same hue,
so they're kind of related
but that might be a better
color for the button overall.
And there we go, going consistency first,
this is looking much better.
If anything though, I feel
like one thing I could do
is reduce the spacing
just a little bit here.
So I will put these in an
auto layout, center them.
I want them to hug the right
side of the screen and then
have only maybe say 16 pixels
instead of 20 between them.
And actually if we do everything right,
I should be able to
shrink this screen down
so that it appears just on one screen
and doesn't kind of run off
and I have to scroll to see it.
So I might just opt for that now.
Let's go ahead and put in
like a ruler that'll just
kind of be my goal to get
everything to below that size.
So maybe at 1420, this
should be the new edge
of the screen and we'll
have this be 20 pixels away.
All right, this is looking good so far.
Now let's move on to
this sidebar right here.
Now with this sidebar,
the alignment looks good.
Like all of these icons
are nice and lined up.
And actually, so let's just remember
that tracking is the active item here.
I'm gonna kind of get that out
of the way just for a second.
But there we go, all of
those are nice and lined up
and now all of these are
nice and lined up and
what I can do is
tidy these up.
When I do that, I have a little bit
of control over how much
space I want between the icon
and the text and how much I
want between the different rows.
And my goal here is twofold.
On one hand, I actually want to include
plenty of space here but not so much
that this feels really
kind of loosey-goosey
and just really overly spaced out.
Like this just seems silly to me.
I would be baffled to hover
over this calendar and find that
it has like a 60 or whatever,
80 pixel tall hover state.
So I do want these kind
of tight but there reaches
a point where if I bring them
in too tight, these icons
get closer to one another
than they are to their labels
and I have that same internal spacing,
external spacing thing going on.
Now I don't actually want to put rules
in between each of the list items here.
So I'm going to include a
little bit more spacing.
Let's say 20 pixels vertically
and then if I try something
like, I don't know,
16 pixels here, like just
keeping it a little bit less
or even it shouldn't be,
yeah, like that could work
but I want to avoid something like this
where the icons feel like their own column
and the text feels like its own column.
So again, just reviewing
some lessons from spacing.
So I'll try something like that,
keep it aligned with the
logo here but otherwise
move it up nice towards
the top of the page here.
Now we have like significantly
cleaned up this area above the table.
In fact, really the
only thing we have here
is this search bar that
applies over the table
but in the name of consistency first,
now what I'm gonna do
is just duplicate this
and change this maybe to say
something like "Search Table."
Now one way to align this
nicely is to put it here
but also since this is
really the only control,
I could consider aligning it
to this side of the screen here
and then just vertically
centering it with this text.
And the nice thing about that is
now it takes up less vertical space,
which means the table can
take up more vertical space.
I will see more data
without having to scroll.
With this much data as
there is right here,
that's not really an
issue but in the real app,
this could be a nice little bonus.
All right, so now we've
done everything else and we
get to the tough part of the
app, which is this table.
Now when I sit down with
a new client and we go
over say a page where
there's a big data table,
a lot of times these
conversations look like me
like really trying to push on them
to figure out everything
we can get rid of.
I just go "Is this necessary?
Who uses this, do we really need this?"
And the reason why is I
want to get my clients
to make the hard choice of
figuring out what's really
essential and then removing
everything that's not.
There's an Antoine de
Saint-Exupery quote that
"Perfection is reached
not when there's nothing
left to add but when there's
nothing left to take away."
And it's a beautiful quote
and it also really applies to UI design.
But it begs the question,
like what is the measure
of what you can take
away and what you can't?
Well in a table, the
stuff that we want to keep
is anything that helps the user decide
what road they're gonna like dig into.
So I'm presuming that if I
click on one of these rows,
I'm gonna bring up the full
information about that order.
This is just some of it,
this is not all the data that
we have about this order.
So I need to click in and
then I'm gonna get all of the
information and maybe that's
gonna be a separate page,
maybe that's gonna be a pop-up,
maybe it's gonna be a slide
over panel, that doesn't matter.
But all I want to do is
keep that information
that helps the user decide
what is my next action here?
Like do I need to dig into something
or is there some real world
action that I need to take?
Anything that helps them decide
that action is what we keep.
So I'm just gonna go through
these columns and use
sample answers somewhat based
on what might be realistic.
All right, let's start with
the reference number here.
So it turns out these reference numbers
are actually really important
and they are used to try
and determine what users are
going to think about next.
So I'm gonna take all these
and because they're not
digit for digit comparable,
I'm going to align them left.
And then also you'll
notice these are blue.
Presumably I can click into these
and they function like any other link.
I'm actually not really a big fan
of having a bunch of other
links throughout a table row
and the reason for that
is because I want the user
to very quickly and easily be
able to click almost anywhere
in this row and then get
to the details of that row.
If then they want to pull up
the details on Esther Howard
or Jake Jones or
whatever, they can do that
there on kind of that drilled in page.
But for right now, anything that's a link,
I'm actually gonna default
to not having it be one.
Now the Sales Rep is an important field.
So we're gonna want to keep
that, that's fair enough.
The company as it turns out, is not
and maybe that's obvious because there
wasn't actually any sample data in here
and then we get to this
interesting situation
where there's a field called Contact
and then there's one
called Site Contact and in
the vast majority of cases,
these are the same person.
So what strategy do we use
here to simplify things?
Well one option is we
could just simply hide
like the site contact or
the normal contact, right?
But to me, that kind of
naive solution doesn't feel
really correct because it sort
of implies that one of these
is more important and that's
not necessarily the case.
It's just that they're usually the same.
So one good strategy here is we could
come up with a custom data display.
So we could like for
instance, join Contact
and Site Contact into
Contact parentheses S
and then we could do something like
if it's just one person, we write that
person's name but if there's two people,
then I'm gonna do something like write
the second person and say "Site Contact."
Now sure, that means that this row
now takes up a little more vertical space
but that is really not a big deal because
we've just saved an entire column that
would have been displayed
on every single row.
This is a great strategy for
kind of hiding excess data
is think can I do a custom
data display to make
the display as compact
as possible in the most
common cases for how the
data is actually structured?
Moving on, the City is
also not super important.
Same thing with the Type,
we can get rid of that.
And now Alerts, we're
actually gonna move this
to the side because
all three of these rows
have an alert and these
are important alerts here.
This is definitely stuff we want to keep
but then this is also kind of an alert
but it's like maybe more of
a note alert or something.
Like there's just some
confusion with these fields.
So I'm actually gonna
take all of this stuff
and just boot it off to
the side for right now.
Now when I keep going
through, I get finally
to sort of the real
challenge of this table
where I have multiple sub rows
for each like actual row in the order
and this is one of those places where
it's really fascinating
and useful to look at
what the real-world use
case of this data is.
Now in the case of this
particular app, I was told
most people are just
gonna do one to two items.
Very rare that you have three or more.
So that's nice because I
know there's very rarely
gonna be all that many
but also it's important
enough that we can't
just remove it entirely.
Like maybe someone who
is looking at this table
of orders is gonna look and
see, oh yeah, this person
ordered two roller blinds or
this person, I don't know,
ordered 100 or this person
ordered some second thing
or third thing or whatever
and they might use that
as an indicator of
remembering what the order is
and then diving into that
order for more details.
So again, I'm gonna think like
what's a custom data display
that'll display the useful
stuff here and no more?
And one way of potentially
doing that is just doing
something like kind of summing
up the products right here.
Now this works nicely in the
case of this particular data.
Everyone just ordered two roller blinds
but you can imagine that
if someone had ordered
like some shades or whatever,
I could just write that
and if they ordered 20 different things,
there'd just be a little dot dot dot
or I'd run over into
multiple lines, et cetera.
And then it turns out that this Status
is largely not needed and
a lot of these actions
aren't super needed most of the time.
Now whenever an action
is not really needed
most of the time, that
makes me think maybe
it's a prime candidate for something like
showing on row hover
or something like that.
So we'll just leave this here for now
and we'll actually come
back to it in a second
because most of the rest of this display
is going to go to Alerts here.
And so now what I want to do
is kind of come up with an intelligent way
of ideally combining these
different types of alerts.
There's one about a minimum deposit.
There's one about a note to call
a customer or before arriving.
There's one about an
install due in one day
and the stock has not been received.
I want to take all of
this and sort of put it
into one easy to understand
alerts or notes type field.
So potentially one way to do this
is maybe I'll even call it "Notes"
and then I can put in a true note here.
I'm actually gonna shrink
it a little bit though.
Use the standard text color as always.
Duplicate for this alert,
put the alert here.
The alert is actually gonna
use the same text color too.
This is kind of part of lightening
is you want to be very judicious
about how you use color.
It's a very common beginner mistake
to overuse color, especially
in things like text.
So we're gonna avoid it when we can.
And maybe what we'll do instead is bring
up the Material Design icons
and find something like,
their Warning icon is a good little
thing that we can put on this page
and that we can color,
that will not look as bad
colored as if we try
and color the whole text
and also no one has to read an icon.
You just glance at it
once and you're good.
So let's actually take a minute
and just kind of straighten up some
of this stuff and just make
it look a little bit tighter.
And there we go, I feel like
I have a good display of both
these notes including the
kind of special alerts here,
easily the most attention-drawing thing
in the entire table,
which feels appropriate
and then I also have included a lot
of the actions in a nice
little hover state right here.
It's not visible by default but anytime
you hover over any of these
rows, you see this little
action button right here
and if you click on it,
you would get a menu of
actions specific to this row
without even needing to open
the row in the first place.
And with that, that brings
us basically to the end.
I guess if there were maybe
a few other things I was
gonna do, kind of just
checking out things at the end,
it would be to lighten
these icons just a bit,
maybe something 60%
opacity seems too little.
70, maybe 80% is kind of
about what I'm looking for.
And the idea there is
just that these icons
kind of hold a lot of visual weight,
yet they're not super, super important.
It's just it's the same
thing with any other
amount of lightening as
I want things to pop only
to the degree that they're
actually really important.
The more pixels something
takes up for being
equal importance, the less it needs to pop
from the background as it
gets bigger and bigger.
So that's looking better.
Maybe I'll do something like
round these corners though
just to give it a little
bit of a softer appearance
and a lot of the other
corners here are rounded.
In fact, I might actually round some
of these other corners even a bit more
which will just give it a nice
kind of friendly appearance.
Yeah, that's kind of cool.
Now I think I'm consistent
at six for most of these.
And then honestly, it's just
a final little detail here
but I do feel like these
are perhaps a bit too thin.
So now that's 36 pixels tall.
Do the same thing here
and there we go.
Overall, we are looking
at what I feel like
is a much better design
and using, honestly,
in my opinion it's
surprisingly few strategies,
really just six main methods
of simplifying our UI,
we have gone from something
that was quite a bit messier
and with a lot of other
elements and colors
and sort of things
competing for our attention
to something that just feels
like it breathes a lot more.
And yeah I know, it's not like
the most heavily branded app in the world.
It's just very neutral
and clean and simple
but it's gonna get the
job done and overall,
users using this will feel like much
more care was put into it and honestly,
this is going to frankly
be easier to use anyways.
So it's really the way to go.
And that's it, folks.
That wraps up simplicity
and the six strategies for getting there.
Now I know I've said this before but
if you've kind of noticed that a lot
of the examples seem a little
bland in the last few lessons,
they don't really seem to have
much of an exciting brand,
they're just kind of
clean, simple and neat,
that's just because I want to focus
on the skills that get you there.
It turns out that a lot of making a brand
more exciting is in color
and typography and imagery
and we're gonna cover
that in a lot of detail.
But making something simple is hard enough
and it's a skill worth
mastering on its own.
Not only, like I said, is it
the most common client request
but it's also something that's
just shockingly difficult.
Like this framework works very well.
It's not easy to do necessarily
and a lot of times you'll
have clients that come
and say "Hey, we'd like
you to just do this,
make up something real quick and simple"
and simple is not quick.
If you've learned anything in this lesson,
you've probably seen that it
takes work to consider exactly
what is necessary and exactly
what is not so necessary
and cut all the unnecessary
stuff or hide it or whatever.
But doing that, those are hard decisions,
it takes work and if it was easy,
they wouldn't be hiring
you in the first place.
So I guess that's just a warning.
Don't lower your rates because
someone says they want a simple design.
All right, take a look at the homework,
post it in the Student
Community when you're done.
Check out the cheat
sheet, there's some good
ideas there and we'll see
you in the next lesson.